A Guide to the Papers Relating to Education in Virginia ca. 1850-1948
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers Relating to Education in Virginia ca. 1850-1948
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-168, -a
Ca. 700 items (2 boxes, 8 linear shelf inches).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These collections are both gifts of James G. Johnson. Accession number 38-168 was given to the Library in 1938, and accession number 38-168-a in 1969.
Scope and Content
The collection contains covering letters and primary source material for Dr. Johnson's History of the Examination, Certification, and Training of Teachers in Virginia. The history covers the period from 1870, when the first state superintendent of public instruction took office, to 1938 when Johnson was superintendent of public schools in Charlottesville, Va. Source material includes teacher certificates, state superintendent memos, teacher examinations and information regarding curriculum, textbooks and financing; the materials were mailed to Johnson in response to a circular of May, 1937, in which he specified the documents he needed. There is also a 1932 dissertation by Thomas Eason, "History of Teacher Certification in Virginia."
The collection also contains a document signed in 1860 by Governor John Letcher appointing justices of the peace for Putnam County, Va.
Miscellaneous additions include programs from the Lane High School Christmas concert, 1946; University of Virginia Concert Band, 1947; an appreciation meeting in honor of Mrs. Cora B. Duke, Jefferson High School, 1947; the Jefferson High School Operetta "College Days," 1947; and the Charlottesville Education Association meeting, 1948. A copy of the resolution in honor of Mrs. Duke is also included.
Arrangement
The material in these collections is divided into three series: material used in Johnson's text, correspondence and enclosures, and additional source material. The second of these series is arranged chronologically by the dates of the correspondence (1937-1941), although the enclosures, like the the rest of the source materials, date from 1850-1938. The third series is subdivided into examination questions and regulations, curriculum and financing, textbook information, teacher's certificates and contracts, state superintendent's memos, Eason's dissertation, clippings, and miscellaneous.
Contents List
- Series I: Materials Used in History
  - Material used for Johnson's text The History of the Examination, Certification, and Training of Teachers in Virginia 1937-1941 (Box 1)
- Series II: Correspondence and Enclosures
  - Correspondence and enclosures 1937-1939, 1941, n.d., 4 folders (Box 1)
- Series III: Additional Source Material
  - Examination Questions and Regulations 1870-1938 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum and Financing 1870-1938 (Box 1)
  - Textbooks 1870-1938 (Box 1)
  - Teacher's Certificates and Contracts 1870-1938, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Superintendent's Memos 1922-1923 (Box 2)
  - "History of Teacher Certification in Virginia," by Thomas Eason 1932 (Box 2)
    MA Education Dissertation - New York University
  - Clippings ca. 1900-1946 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous ca. 1850-1939 (Box 2)